<modelComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
    <citations>
        <citation ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.Citation">
            <collectiveTitle>Collins W.J. , N. Bellouin, M. Doutriaux-Boucher, N. Gedney, T. Hinton,
                C.D. Jones, S. Liddicoat, G. Martin, F. O'Connor, J. Rae, C. Senior, I. Totterdell,
                and S. Woodward (2008) Evaluation of the HadGEM2 model.. Meteorological Office
                Hadley Centre, Technical Note 74,</collectiveTitle>
            <date>2008-01-01 00:00:00</date>
            <location>http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/publications/HCTN/HCTN_74.pdf</location>
            <title>Collins W.J. (2008)</title>
        </citation>
        <citation ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.Citation">
            <collectiveTitle>Bellouin N., O. Boucher, J. Haywood, C. Johnson, A. Jones, J. Rae, and
                S. Woodward. (2007) Improved representation of aerosols for HadGEM2.. Meteorological
                Office Hadley Centre, Technical Note 73, March 2007</collectiveTitle>
            <date>2007-01-01 00:00:00</date>
            <location>http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/publications/HCTN/HCTN_73.pdf</location>
            <title>Bellouin N. (2007)</title>
        </citation>
    </citations>
    <description>The HadGEM2-ES model was a two stage development from HadGEM1, representing
        improvements in the physical model (leading to HadGEM2-AO) and the addition of earth system
        components and coupling (leading to HadGEM2-ES). [1] The HadGEM2-AO project targeted two key
        features of performance: ENSO and northern continent land-surface temperature biases. The
        latter had a particularly high priority in order for the model to be able to adequately
        model continental vegetation. Through focused working groups a number of mechanisms that
        improved the performance were identified. Some known systematic errors in HadGEM1, such as
        the Indian monsoon, were not targeted for attention in HadGEM2-AO. HadGEM2-AO substantially
        improved mean SSTs and wind stress and improved tropical SST variability compared to
        HadGEM1. The northern continental warm bias in HadGEM1 has been significantly reduced. The
        power spectrum of El Nino is made worse, but other aspects of ENSO are improved. Overall
        there is a noticeable improvement from HadGEM1 to HadGEM2-AO when comparing global climate
        indices. [2] In HadGEM2-ES the vegetation cover is better than in the previous HadCM3LC
        model especially for trees, and the productivity is better than in the non-interactive
        HadGEM2-AO model. The presence of too much bare soil in Australia though may cause problems
        for the dust emissions scheme. The simulation of global soil and biomass carbon stores are
        good and agree well with observed estimates except in regions of errors in the vegetation
        cover. HadGEM2-ES compares well with the C4MIP ensemble of models. The distribution of NPP
        is much improved relative to HadCM3LC. At a site level the component carbon fluxes validate
        better against observations and in particular the timing of the growth season is
        significantly improved. The ocean biology (HadOCC) allows the completion of the carbon cycle
        and the provision of di-methyl sulphide (DMS) emissions from phytoplankton. DMS is a
        significant source of sulphate aerosol over the oceans. The diat-HadOCC scheme is an
        improvement over the standard HadOCC scheme as it differentiates between diatom and
        non-diatom plankton. These have different processes for removing carbon from the surface to
        the deep ocean, and respond differently to iron nutrients. The HadOCC scheme performs well
        with very reasonable plankton distributions, rates of productivity and emissions of DMS. The
        diat-HadOCC scheme has slightly too low levels of productivity which requires further tuning
        to overcome. The additions of a tropospheric chemistry scheme, new aerosol species (organic
        carbon and dust) and coupling between the chemistry and sulphate aerosols have significantly
        enhanced the earth system capabilities of the model. This has improved the tropospheric
        ozone distribution and the distributions of aerosol species compared to observations, both
        of which are important for climate forcing. Including interactive earth system components
        has not significantly affected the physical performance of the model.</description>
    <longName>HadGEM2-ES (2009) atmosphere: HadGAM2 (N96L38); ocean: HadGOM2 (lat: 1.0-0.3 lon: 1.0
        L40); land-surface/vegetation: MOSES2 and TRIFFID; tropospheric chemistry: UKCA; ocean
        biogeochemistry: diat-HadOCC</longName>
    <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
        <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.502082</createDate>
        <encodings>
            <encoding>json</encoding>
            <encoding>xml</encoding>
            <encoding>html</encoding>
            <encoding>xml-metafor-cim-v1</encoding>
        </encodings>
        <id>a40469ff-1b4a-4cd1-906f-bb754010ecf7</id>
        <institute>mohc</institute>
        <language>en</language>
        <project>cmip5</project>
        <sortKey>AAHADGEM2-ES</sortKey>
        <source>mohc</source>
        <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
        <typeDisplayName>Model</typeDisplayName>
        <typeSortKey>AA</typeSortKey>
    </meta>
    <releaseDate>2009-11-01 00:00:00</releaseDate>
    <responsibleParties>
        <responsibleParty ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.ResponsibleParty">
            <address>Fitzroy Road,Exeter,Devon,EX1 3PB,UK</address>
            <email>bill.collins@metoffice.gov.uk</email>
            <individualName>Dr Bill Collins</individualName>
            <organisationName>Met Office Hadley Centre</organisationName>
            <url>www.metoffice.gov.uk</url>
        </responsibleParty>
    </responsibleParties>
    <shortName>HadGEM2-ES</shortName>
    <subComponents>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The model includes interactive schemes for sulphate, sea salt, black carbon
                from fossil-fuel emissions, organic carbon from fossil-fuel emissions, mineral dust,
                and biomass-burning aerosols. The model also includes a fixed monthly climatology of
                mass-mixing ratios of secondary organic aerosols from terpene emissions (biogenic
                aerosols).</description>
            <longName>Aerosols</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.616451</createDate>
                <id>417a325c-1628-4e67-a6e2-fdc321420b16</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Atmospheric domains covered by the aerosol model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>AerosolSchemeScope</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Whole atmosphere</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Decription of the basic approximations made in the Aerosol
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Modal scheme</value>
                        <value>Mass as a tracer</value>
                        <value>Number inferred from prescribed size distributions</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Prognostic variables of the aerosol model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfPrognosticVariables</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>3D mass/volume mixing ratio for aerosols</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Number of tracers in the aerosol model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>NumberOfTracers</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>21</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Aerosol calculations are generalised into families of
                        species.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>FamilyApproach</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>No</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Mathematical method deployed to solve the time evolution of the
                        prognostic variables. uses AtmosphericChemistry time stepping: Aerosol model
                        uses the same time-stepping framework as the one of the Atmospheric
                        chemistry model. specific time stepping (operator splitting): The Aerosol
                        model use its own time-step and all the processes are decoupled; the time
                        evolution is calculated sequentially and the tendencies are cumulated.
                        specific time stepping (integrated): The Aerosol model uses its own
                        time-step and all the processes having an impact on the time evolution are
                        taken into account and solved simultaneously.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Method</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Uses AtmosphericChemistry time stepping</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Aerosols</shortName>
            <type>Aerosols</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The model incorporates the Met Office's New Dynamics framework that
                provides a non-hydrostatic, fully compressible, deep atmosphere formulation with
                fewer approximations to the basic equations; semi-Lagrangian advection of all
                prognostic variables except density, permitting relatively long timesteps to be used
                at higher resolution; a conservative and monotone treatment of tracer transport; and
                improved geostrophic adjustment properties bringing better balance to the coupling.
                The model includes interactive modelling of atmospheric aerosols, driven by surface
                and elevated emissions and including tropospheric chemical processes as well as
                physical removal processes such as washout. The aerosol species represented in the
                model are sulphate, black carbon, biomass smoke, sea salt, organic carbon, mineral
                dust and a biogenic climatology. The atmospheric component has a horizontal
                resolution of 1.25 degrees of latitude by 1.875 degrees of longitude with 38 layers
                in the vertical extending to over 39 km in height. The model uses the Arakawa C-grid
                horizontally and the Charney-Phillips grid vertically. The atmospheric timestep
                period is 30 minutes (48 timesteps per day).</description>
            <longName>Atmosphere</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.666888</createDate>
                <id>95d03f15-a669-4dd2-9db6-84b8ee4257d5</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Type of atmospheric model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ModelFamily</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>AGCM</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Basic approximations made in the atmospheric model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Non-hydrostatic</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>How the volcanoes effect is modeled in the atmophere.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>VolcanoesImplementation</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Via stratospheric aerosols optical thickness</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Details of volcanoes implementation method.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>VolcanoesImplementationMethod</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Monthly stratospheric optical depths</value>
                        <value>At 550nm</value>
                        <value>Prescribed for quarter-spheres (90S-30S</value>
                        <value>30S-0</value>
                        <value>0-30N</value>
                        <value>30N-90N)</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time adaptation of the orography.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>OrographyType</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Present-day</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Atmosphere</shortName>
            <type>Atmosphere</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The atmospheric chemistry component of HadGEM2-ES is a configuration of the
                United Kingdom Chemistry and Aerosols (UKCA) model (O'Connor et al., 2009; 2010;
                www.ukca.ac.uk) running a relatively thorough description of inorganic odd oxygen
                (Ox), nitrogen (NOy), hydrogen (HOx), and carbon monoxide (CO) chemistry with
                near-explicit treatment of methane (CH4), ethane (C2H6), propane (C3H8), and acetone
                (Me2CO) degradation (including formaldehyde (HCHO), acetaldehyde (MeCHO), peroxy
                acetyl nitrate (PAN), and peroxy propionyl nitrate (PPAN)). It makes use of 25
                tracers and represents 41 species. Large-scale transport, convective transport, and
                boundary layer mixing are treated. The chemistry scheme accounts for 25 photolytic
                reactions, 83 bimolecular reactions, and 13 uni- and termolecular
                reactions.</description>
            <longName>Atmospheric Chemistry</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.696876</createDate>
                <id>1c0e2efc-2a5e-4de5-b9fa-ec70e86d96ba</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Atmospheric domains covered by the atmospheric chemistry
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ChemSchemeScope</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Troposphere</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Description of th basic approximations made in the Atmospheric
                        Chemistry model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>See component description</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Prognostic variables of the Atmospheric Chemistry
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfPrognosticVariables</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>3D mass/mixing ratio for gas</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Number of tracers in the Atmospheric Chemistry model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>NumberOfTracers</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>25</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Atmospheric Chemistry calculations are generalised into families of
                        species.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>FamilyApproach</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>No</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Chemistry transport scheme turbulence is coupled with chemical
                        reactivity.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>CouplingWithChemicalReactivity</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>No</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Mathematical method deployed to solve the evolution of a given
                        variable. operator splitting: All the processes are decoupled, the time
                        evolution is calculated sequentially and the tendencies are cumulated; the
                        global evolution depends on the order the cumulation performed. integrated:
                        All the processes having an impact on the time evolution are taken into
                        account and solved simultaneously.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Method</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Other</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>TimeSteppingMethod</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>The atmospheric chemistry model uses the same timestep as the
                            atmosphere model</value>
                        <value>But has an internal timestep of 5 mins for calculating the
                            reactions</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Atmospheric Chemistry</shortName>
            <type>AtmosphericChemistry</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The major ice sheets (Greenland and Antarctica) and minor ice caps
                (Ellesmere, Devon and Baffin islands, Iceland, Svalbard, Novaya and Severnaya
                Zemlya, and Stikine) are depicted as static ice. They are initialised with a snow
                depth of 50,000 mm of water equivalent. Further ablation or accumulation has an
                impact on sea level. Runoff follows the river routing scheme and enters the oceans
                at predefined river outflow points. Calving at the coastal boundaries is simulated
                through a fresh water flux to the ocean evenly distributed over the area of observed
                icebergs in both hemispheres. The value of the freshwater flux is calculated to
                exactly balance the time mean ice sheet surface mass balance over the pre-industrial
                control simulation.</description>
            <longName>Land Ice</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.742537</createDate>
                <id>a7b0121e-bd3f-4bf8-8035-f3a2fa814600</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Method by which ice sheets are coupled to ice shelves</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>CouplingIceSheet-IceShelves</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/A</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Definition of property name LandIceAlbedo required</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LandIceAlbedo</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Prescribed</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Land Ice</shortName>
            <type>LandIce</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The second version of the U.K. Met Office Surface Exchange Scheme
                (MOSES-II) (Cox et al., 1999; Essery et al., 2003) is used. This allows tiling of
                land surface heterogeneity using nine different surface types. A separate surface
                energy balance is calculated for each tile and area-weighted grid box mean fluxes
                are computed, which are thus much more realistic than when a single surface type is
                assumed. In addition, vegetation leaf area is allowed to vary seasonally, providing
                a more realistic representation of seasonal changes in surface fluxes. Tiling of
                coastal grid points allows separate treatment of land and sea fractions. This in
                combination with the increased ocean model resolution greatly improves the
                coastline, particularly in island regions.</description>
            <longName>Land Surface</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.760018</createDate>
                <id>56bf3bfd-484d-43f4-8b83-be0f8d1b7c39</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Decription of the basic approximations made in the LandSurface
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Linearisation of the surface energy balance equations</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>History of parent models.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Genealogy</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Other</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Specify the treatment of land surface coupling with the Atmosphere
                        model component.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>CouplingWithAtmosphere</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Implicit</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Types of land cover defined in the land surface
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LandCoverTypes</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Bare soil</value>
                        <value>Ice</value>
                        <value>Urban</value>
                        <value>Vegetated</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Specify which prognostic variables are included in the land surface
                        scheme.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfPrognosticVariables</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Canopy heat content</value>
                        <value>Canopy skin temperature</value>
                        <value>Canopy snow content</value>
                        <value>Canopy water content</value>
                        <value>Snow albedo</value>
                        <value>Snow mass</value>
                        <value>Soil heat content</value>
                        <value>Soil ice content</value>
                        <value>Soil moisture</value>
                        <value>Soil temperature</value>
                        <value>Surface skin temperature</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Is land surface tiling common to all land surface
                        subcomponents?</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Tiling</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Common to all LS subcomponents</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Describe the method of tiling used</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>TilingMethod</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Dynamic</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Specify the treatment of water to ocean</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>WaterTreatment</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>All water sent to ocean (with a lag)</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Value of the lag duration of the water discharge into
                        ocean.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LagOfWaterDischarge</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Simulated by river flow model</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Is the time stepping framework used the same as that used in the
                        atmosphere model component?</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Method</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Use Atmosphere time step</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Land Surface</shortName>
            <type>LandSurface</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The ocean component is based on the Bryan-Cox code (Bryan, 1969; Cox, 1984)
                and follows the ocean component of HadGEM1 (Johns et al., 2006) very closely. The
                model uses a latitude-longitude grid with a zonal resolution of 1 degree, and a
                meridional resolution of 1 degree between the poles and 30 degrees, from which it
                increases smoothly to 0.333 degrees at the equator - giving a grid of 360 x 216
                points. It has 40 unevenly spaced levels in the vertical, with enhanced resolution
                near the surface better to resolve the mixed layer and thermocline. The forward
                timestep period is 1 hour, with a mixing timestep of once per day. HadGEM2 uses a
                bathymetry derived from the Smith and Sandwell (1997) 1/30 degrees depth dataset
                merged with ETOPO5 (1988) 1/12 degrees data at high latitudes, interpolated to the
                model grid and smoothed using a five-point (1:4:1) two-dimensional filter. Where
                this procedure obstructs important narrow pathways (e.g., Denmark Strait,
                Faroes-Shetland Channel, Vema Channel, and around the Indonesian archipelago), the
                bathymetry is adjusted to allow some flow at realistic depths (with reference to
                Thompson, 1995). The land masks for the ocean grid differs from that used for the
                atmosphere model, due to the differences in model resolutions. To enable daily
                coupling between the models a tiling scheme has been introduced. For each atmosphere
                grid box, fractions of the fluxes can be coupled to land, sea and sea ice models so
                that the total flux is conserved - though locally the flux may not be conserved so
                diagnosis can be difficult. The only ancillary flux used by the ocean model is to
                enable a balance in the freshwater flux to be maintained, since the accumulation of
                frozen water on land is not returned into the freshwater cycle, i.e. there is no
                representation of icebergs calving off ice shelves. The ancillary flux is used to
                add freshwater back into the model, calibrated from a HadGEM2 reference integration
                to give a balanced freshwater budget.</description>
            <longName>Ocean</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.853198</createDate>
                <id>33e6fcaa-ee40-41f2-b9fb-c6ff592f9144</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Type of oceanic model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ModelFamily</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>OGCM</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Basic approximations made in the oceanic model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Boussinesq</value>
                        <value>Non-hydrostatic</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>List of the prognostic variables of the model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfPrognosticVariables</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Potential temperature</value>
                        <value>Salinity</value>
                        <value>SSH</value>
                        <value>U-velocity</value>
                        <value>V-velocity</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Formulation for equation of state of sea water.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>EquationOfState</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Other</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Hypothesis on sea water freezing point.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>FreezingPoint</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Fixed</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Hypothesis on sea water specific heat.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>SpecificHeat</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Fixed</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Sea water freezing temperature.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>FreezingPointValue</shortName>
                    <units>degC</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>-1.8</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Value of the sea water specific heat.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>SpecificHeatValue</shortName>
                    <units>J.kg-1.K-1</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>3988.0</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Distribution of freshwater fluxes from rivers into
                        ocean.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>RiverMouthMixing</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Addition of surface freshwater at river mouth</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Mixing of isolated sea water with ocean.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>IsolatedSeasMixing</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Yes</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time evolution of the bathymetry - either fixed to reference date
                        below or evolving at paleo timescales.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BathymetryType</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Fixed</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time period for which fixed bathymetry is defined.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ReferenceDate</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Present-day</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Numerical method used by the horizontal discretization
                        scheme.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>SchemeMethod</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Finite differences</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Method used to deal with north pole singularities.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>PoleSingularityTreatment</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Artificial island</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>How the different quantities are located within a grid
                        cell.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Staggering</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Arakawa B-grid</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time stepping scheme for tracers.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Tracers</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Leap-frog + Asselin filter</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time stepping scheme for barotropic solver.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BarotropicSolver</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Leap-frog + Asselin filter</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time stepping scheme for baroclinic momentum.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BaroclinicMomentum</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Leap-frog + Asselin filter</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Time step of the model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>TimeStep</shortName>
                    <units>seconds</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>3600</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Ocean</shortName>
            <type>Ocean</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>There is a simple prognostic ecosystem model (the Diat-HadOCC model), with
                three nutrients (combined nitrate and ammonium, dissolved silicate and dissolved
                iron), two phytoplankton (diatoms and other phytoplankton), one zooplankton and
                three detrital compartments (detrital nitrogen, detrital carbon and detrital
                silicate). There are also two prognostic tracers that are only used in a diagnostic
                capacity (i.e. their concentrations are affected by, but do not affect, the other
                compartments): these are dissolved ammonium and dissolved oxygen. Nitrogen is used
                as the model currency. The diatoms have a variable silicate:nitrate ratio, so diatom
                silicate is another compartment. All three of the detrital compartments sink with a
                constant velocity, and are remineralised at a rate that is depth-dependent. The
                zooplankton and both phytoplankton compartments have fixed elemental carbon:nitrogen
                ratios which allow the flows of carbon through the ecosystem to be linked to the
                corresponding nitrogen flows. As well as the ecosystem compartments listed above
                dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) and total alkalinity (TAlk) are included as
                prognostic tracers. Those two compartments, along with the model temperature and
                salinity, are used to calculate the ocean surface pCO2, the air-sea flux of CO2 and
                the ocean pH. The air-sea fluxes of CO2 and DMS are each calculated every ocean
                time-step and their daily means are passed through the coupler to the atmosphere
                each day.</description>
            <longName>Ocean Biogeo Chemistry</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.805687</createDate>
                <id>0e79e220-aab8-47c3-9333-04a1ad9f2862</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Description of the basic approximations made in the biogeo
                        chemistry model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Eulerian model</value>
                        <value>N3 P2 Z1 D1 ecosystem; no diel cycle</value>
                        <value>Constant detrital sinking rate</value>
                        <value>Constant (carbonate) rain ratio</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Prognostic variables of the ocean biogeo chemistry
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfPrognosticVariables</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Dissolved inorganic nitrogen (nitrate+ammonia); dissolved silicate;
                            dissolved iron; diatoms; other phytoplankton; zooplankton; diatom
                            silicate; detrital nitrogen; detrital carbon; detrital silicate;
                            dissolved inorganic carbon; total alkalinity; dissolved oxygen.</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>List of tracers to which a damping is applied.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfTracers</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value/>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Southern boundary of the tracers damping zone.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LatMin</shortName>
                    <units>degN</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/a</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Northern boundary of the tracers damping zone.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LatMax</shortName>
                    <units>degN</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/a</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Western boundary of the tracers damping zone.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LonMin</shortName>
                    <units>degE</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/a</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Eastern boundary of the tracers damping zone.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LonMax</shortName>
                    <units>degE</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/a</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Upper level of the tracers damping zone.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>UpperLevel</shortName>
                    <units>meters</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/a</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Lower level of the tracers damping zone.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>LowerLevel</shortName>
                    <units>meters</units>
                    <values>
                        <value>N/a</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Method for transport for ocean biogeochemistry.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Method</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Online</value>
                        <value>Different from Ocean Tracers</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Description of the specificities of the ocean biogeochemistry
                        transport method (compared to Ocean tracers one).</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>MethodCharacteristics</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>UTOPIA with flux-limiter</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Ocean Biogeo Chemistry</shortName>
            <type>OceanBiogeoChemistry</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
        <subComponent ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ModelComponent">
            <description>The sea-ice model is split between the atmosphere and ocean model
                components. The atmosphere part calculates the atmosphere-ice heat fluxes, the
                diffusive heat flux through the ice, the ice surface temperature and surface
                melting. This allows the diurnal cycle of the surface temperature to be modelled
                whilst only coupling between the atmosphere and ocean components once a day. The
                ocean part deals with the remaining thermodynamics, calculates basal melting by heat
                supplied from the mixed layer, keeps account of snow and ice thickness changes
                including conversion of submerged snow to ice, and deals with ice dynamics
                (including ridging) using daily mean fields of the atmospheric forcings supplied via
                coupling routines. A multiple ice thickness category model which solves the basic
                equation of Thorndike et al. (1975), is used to capture the sub-gridscale ice
                thickness distribution. The model uses five ice categories plus open water (leads).
                Ice thickness affects many sea ice properties and processes, including the growth
                rate, ice strength and surface energy fluxes. As ice thickness can vary greatly
                within the grid box length scale, a multiple ice category model should lead to an
                improved representation of sea ice processes.</description>
            <longName>Sea Ice</longName>
            <meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.shared.DocMetaInfo">
                <createDate>2014-12-17 12:04:38.925866</createDate>
                <id>cd6784d5-f8af-4294-a353-408e47266e11</id>
                <institute>mohc</institute>
                <language>en</language>
                <project>cmip5</project>
                <source>mohc</source>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </meta>
            <properties>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Description of the basic approximations made in the sea ice
                        model.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>BasicApproximations</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Multiple ice thickness categories (5 + open water); zero layer
                            thermodynamics; EVP dynamics and ridging scheme</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>List of sea ice prognostic variables.</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>ListOfPrognosticVariables</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Ice concentration (per thickness category)</value>
                        <value>Grid box mean ice thickness (per thickness category)</value>
                        <value>Grid box mean snow thickness (per thickness category)</value>
                        <value>Surface snow or ice temperature (per thickness category)</value>
                        <value>Ice velocities</value>
                        <value>Internal ice stress tensors</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Type of scheme used to represent sea ice</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>SchemeType</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Other</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>SeaIceRepresentationScheme</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Multiple thickness categories</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
                <property ontologyTypeKey="cim.1.software.ComponentProperty">
                    <description>Specify what timestep sea-ice operates on</description>
                    <isRepresented>True</isRepresented>
                    <shortName>Method</shortName>
                    <values>
                        <value>Use Ocean time step</value>
                    </values>
                </property>
            </properties>
            <shortName>Sea Ice</shortName>
            <type>SeaIce</type>
            <types>
                <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
            </types>
        </subComponent>
    </subComponents>
    <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
    <types>
        <type>cim.1.software.ModelComponent</type>
    </types>
</modelComponent>
